hello I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob
iding Our Guest today is Paul gev vice
president of strategy Business
Development and analytics at Surfline on
the podcast we talk with Paul about the
Strategic pitfalls in modeling total
addressable Market how fremium should
work and why surfline's current success
was actually 38 years in the
making hey Paul thanks so much for
joining us on the podcast today I
appreciate you guys having me on I've
been looking forward to it and Jacob
always nice to chat with you just a guy
in Ohio ready to talk about surfing
that's what we're here for today so
let's talk surfing I wanted to get a
little bit of background Paul so I know
you're currently at Surf line but you've
done some really interesting things
leading up to this that led to the job
at Surf line so tell us a bit about what
you did before in consumer subscriptions
and then how you transition to Surfline
yeah I guess it's a non-traditional
entry into Tech so I worked in the media
industry for for the past eight years
proceeding my time in Surfline and I
started off in the finance department
working on traditional linear media so
broadcast media cable things like that
and two or three years after I started
Netflix really started picking up steam
and we started seeing further adoption
in spot viewership and so I got really
enamored with the streaming side of the
business and so a couple years later I
got the opportunity to work on some of
our sod products and I spent the last
four or five years at Discovery
Communications which is now Warner
Brothers Discovery working on some of
their rest products I transitioned from
Finance to strategy and analytics got
lucky enough to get a shot there and
then towards the end of my tenure IID
moved to LA I was originally based in
London and I moved to LA with my wife
and I started surfing a tremendous
amount like I was surfing four or five
times a week and I was using an app
called Surfline I got addicted to the
product I thought it was great and I got
lucky enough to get introduced to the
CEO at Surf line at the time his name
was Jeff Berg and we had some
conversation they had just raised some
capital from the churning group and he
was looking to build out a strategy and
analytics team at Surfline I thought it
was a great opportunity to work on
something I was passionate about and get
some experience in a different side of
consumer subscription right because
espod was intrinsically a little bit
different than mobile application
subscription I've been here for three
years now I oversee strategy analytics
and then all of the other commercial
functions so marketing ad sales product
growth as well and loving it what's a
culture like at Sur one is it just a
bunch of crazy Surfers or kind of a mix
you would think so and that was kind of
my perception I thought we'd come in and
it would be that stereotypical surf
culture that you'd see and there's some
of that but I was surprised when I came
in at how much talent there was at the
company and how many Tech native people
there were we had at the time our CMO
came from Apple our CEO at the time Kyle
Laughlin had come from Amazon and there
were all these people that worked in big
tech for many years and so there was
this half culture of we're really
focused on on surf culture surf
Community but there was also a work hard
mentality and people really wanted to
innovate and build products that would
make Surfers lives much better kind of
in the surf industry there aren't a lot
of jobs where you have a great balance
between culture and Innovation and
that's what we found in Surf line and
it's been fantastic it's funny coming
into Revenue cat was kind of the
opposite like everybody else at Revenue
cat surfed and my first experience with
Revenue cat in person was a little surf
offsite in
2019 it was the last offsite we could do
at the beach we went from five out of
five Surfers to like five out of seven
and I was like this is over for us it
was just serendipitous but the first
five of us actually bonded over surfing
also apps though but I mean it's
interesting it doesn't surprise me that
especially I think California being the
tech Hub of the world more or less and
also being one of the best surfing
coasts in the world if not the best you
end up with a lot of folks that are
probably passionate about both of those
things and surf line as a product like
there are other players in Surf
technology but I don't think anybody's
at the level that Surfline is in terms
of reach and dominance and functionality
and all of those things so I'm sure
David you know that I mean I'm going to
steal your story Paul but the story of
surf line you know how it got started it
was originally a phone call like that's
where surf line comes from it that's
right it started off as like an
answering machine in somebody's garage
or something like this yeah it was like
a paper phone number that you would call
it there was actually a fax as well you
could get a fax
like in the 80s right
been 1985 is when it was founded
consumer subscription app in 2023
founded in 1985 as a 1 1900 number that
might be a record I think we hold a
bunch of Records we call ourselves the
38-year-old startup right so we're found
it in 1985 and originally it was a paper
phone number and then facts and then
when the web started becoming a thing
when the internet started coming to its
prominence we had a free website for a
period of time and we actually launched
our subscription in 2001 so to kind of
date that that's six years before
Netflix launched their subscription so
we're better than Netflix in at least
one way at least the founders had the
foresight to move in that direction
pretty early on but there's been a
serious Evolution even since 2001 but
it's a crazy story it's very
unconventional yeah I thought all Trails
was early to subscriptions I didn't
realize yall started your first consumer
subscription product in 2001 that's
crazy yeah it wasn't really a key Focus
back there 2001 if you think about the
market back then there weren't many
digital subscription products that were
out there so it was a challenging
proposition in the beginning to get
people comfortable with a recurring
payment through some digital product on
the web and so it took many years to
kind of and technologically like how'
you even do it it's not like today when
there's tooling and all of this stuff to
make payments so much easier than it was
20 years ago 100% and again predat to me
quite a bit so I can't say but they
definitely hacked some stuff together
and got it working so well I think
that's a good segue into the first topic
I wanted to discuss and that's
understanding and calculating Tam total
addressable Market in
1985 I don't know that the founders
could have ever imagined how the Tam
would grow but then also what it would
actually look like in 2023 so yeah tell
me about your thinking on Tam and how to
calculate it and common mistakes on how
people think about Tam Tam is really
important for a company like Surfline
when you think about the total
addressable Market how many people are
out there that might be willing to pay
for your product there aren't 100
million Surfers in the US so we have a
niche T and it's very important we
understand what that addressable Market
is because it should influence our
product strategy our monetization
strategy all of those things I'm sure
the founders weren't thinking about Tam
back then right back they didn't have to
pitch anybody I mean look surf
forecasting wasn't really a thing back
in 1985 we kind of pioneered yeah I
learned that recently that even like
wave forecasting wasn't until recent
times that they even could predict when
there were going to be swells and things
like this big shout out to Sean Collins
for doing that back in the 80s but today
it's really important for us and when we
think about Tam really what we're trying
to calculate is what is the size of the
opportunity in the market there's some
great use cases for Tam the big one
being really it's like a sales tactic to
be candid right from a tam standpoint
you're going out to investors talking
about how big the opportunity is telling
a story there the flaws come when you
start trying to calculate the
addressable audience from a modeling
standpoint and what you should do
strategically from product strategy and
monetization strategy so I'll give you
an example let's say we're a golf
company and you go out the market and
you say okay there's 50 million golfers
in the US that's our Tam if you're
launching a subscription product you'll
probably find pretty quickly after you
launch the product that there's 50
million golfers out there but there
aren't 50 million golfers who play golf
on a frequent basis maybe it's 20
million that actually play on a frequent
basis and so you're kind of omitting a
key factor which is commitment you
really have to move from a metric Tam to
another metric that's used in the
industry called the serviceable
addressable Market Sam and that's the
biggest issue that I see with most
companies that are going out to Market
and putting together their commercial
strategy is they'll use Tam and they'll
model everything off of that and they'll
say okay well Tam's 100 million people
and we're going to go and acquire like
5% and call it a day and that's how they
model things out but in reality when you
start digging in you find out that hey
really our product isn't something
that's going to service all 100 million
of these people it's going to service
some fraction because there are other
variables that I've omitted and so it's
really important to figure out what the
serviceable addressable Market is and
there's a number of different variables
that you should look at one is
commitment is very important especially
in a niche direct consumer space you
want people who are committed because
they are going to be paying a
subscription and that's often omitted in
the modeling and the estimates that
people put together that's the biggest
one to be candid that I see out when
people are calculating the metric how do
you think about the Sam cuz I sometimes
feel like Sam is actually the true Tam
like you said like Tam is like the Tam
people dream Sam is actually your Tam
but I think as an argument and maybe
this goes into more long range modeling
s of short range modeling but that your
Sam should maybe evolve into eat more of
that t like it depends on what the
limits to serviceability are right like
if it's commitment golfers are not going
to become twice as committed by 2028
right like I'm not going to read that in
a garden report or whatever but they
might become twice as open to using
software or something like that so how
do you think about Sam evolution in
regards to like Surface versus address
difference I think it's all about timing
candidly so you should always have Tam
in the back of your mind because you as
a product leader in the space you're
going to look out and say my product's
going to continue to evolve serviceable
for me in the future is different than
what it is today and so it's always
important to have that Tam number in the
back of your head and figure out what
the Delta is between your Tam and your
currently serviceable addressable market
so I like using the serviceable
addressable market for a couple reasons
and the reason it's important more than
anything is if you have a good idea of
what's serviceable it can really
influence your commercial strategy so
another example if your Tam is really
small or your serviceable addressable
Market is really small you might want to
wait your investment in arpu more than
you do subscription growth you might say
okay really we might reach saturation a
little bit quicker than we originally
thought we should focus on growing arpol
or maybe the strategy is hey we know
that we're going to get pretty
significant market share within this
audience we should look at adjacent
audiences or new geographies and this is
an exercise that a lot of big companies
do and you look at the growth of
companies like Spotify for example the
growth isn't coming predominantly from
the us anymore it's they've realized hey
we're starting to saturate a little bit
in the US we're going to look at markets
outside of the US and start getting
market share there same thing with a lot
of the big espod companies so it's
really important that you have your
finger on the heartbeat there of what is
actually serviceable and addressable
today but not lose sight of what is
possible in the future yeah you can you
use the word investment but you end up
putting effort into something that you
can't change once you've hit the limits
or at least like the reasonable limits
of your Channel or your Market or
whatever you're pulling into it's just
wasted money you on the acquisition side
Revenue cat I think we've had the
similar experience where like I think if
we had gone full into go to market three
years ago we probably would have been in
a lot of pain because of shortfalls in
our product Market fit and our ability
to service those customers and things
like this so maybe unintentionally we
strategically didn't but now after three
years of prodct development okay like
now actually maybe each dollar we invest
on growth is probably going to have a
much higher Roi now that the products
position that same has like increased
for us which kind of I don't know when
you're thinking about managing a company
over many years and benchmarking it
against peers and benchmarking it
against maybe Pierce outside of your
space can be a little I don't know
depressing is the right word I don't
know like sometimes you're like I know
for me personally like I look at other
SAS companies that have essentially
infinite Tams and they'll just be like
yeah we're just double them every year
we spend $200 million on sales and
marketing and then we add $20 million in
revenue and we just do it over and over
again and revenue cat exists in a niche
in its own which is this like consumer
subscription we have some of the same
mechanics where it's not an infinite Tam
at least not today I'm curious how do
you think about in surfing too as the
particular mechanics of it there's some
interesting natural limits to surfing's
Total addressable Market because for
anybody who surfed especially in some of
the more crowded places in California
there's only so many people that can
surve practically at a spot the laws of
efficient markets really start to play
out once a spot becomes too busy can
maybe only handle so much traffic so
there's sort of a natural economic upper
bound do you take that into your models
like how many surf spots are there that
are undeveloped and if you have that
list of undeveloped surf spots I would
appreciate you sending it to me so that
I can go there but we could save that
for off the Pod we don't have a list of
undeveloped surf spots but you're right
it's a finite list of locations just
like naturally in surfing there's only a
certain number of locations you can surf
and you're dependent on the conditions
being reasonable for surfing if it's
flat you can't actually get out I'll a
few things though surfing is one of the
sports that's been growing quite quickly
right it's had a crazy run since even
the last 10 years has been crazy not
just surfing but there's a lot of other
sports that have seen the same adoption
I think Golf and pickle ball and all
these these Sports have really been
picking up but in surfing now we are
seeing some other Innovation that's
interesting there building surf Parks
all around the world so these are
artificial wave pools where you can go
surfing and it's interesting because a
lot of these pools are being built in
places where people don't have access to
the beach so it could be right now there
a huge pool being built in Munich for
example and funny enough there's a lot
of German Surfers who are just traveling
to Morocco and SP and different places
every time I went to Central America
everybody at the surf camp was German
just about yeah yeah we do see a lot of
growth in the industry coming from those
surf Parks right it's going to drive a
lot of adoption and again with
demographics that are non-traditional in
surfing which is also very interesting
because these are urban areas people
don't have access to the beach obviously
living close to the beach is very
expensive so this might bring in cohorts
of surfers who couldn't traditionally
afford to go surfing it's a challenge
for sure well especially if you're a
surf forecaster because if you create a
wave pool that has consistent waves it
must create some interesting product
strategy challenges for you guys it does
to degree we kind of have two parts of
the business one is surf forecasting the
second piece are the cameras and the
camera technology that we're developing
and there's some interesting synergies
between the camera technology we're
developing and you surf Park so I don't
want to give away too much here but this
is where 20 30 years in you guys can
leverage a brand into that market shift
which not all companies all scales have
that luxury but there's a good example
of widening your serviceable addressable
market right like looking at the tan
from a top down perspective what's going
to shift and surf ranches and surf parks
are I think going to be I live in Ohio I
would really love for somebody to put an
indoor surf Park up within five hours
that would change everything for me to
continue my hobby you know in terms of
strategy that's the kind of stuff you
want to be thinking about with Tam I
feel I'm curious when I learned
Computing in addressable Market I was
taught two methods right there's the
top- down method well like there's a
million Surfers and like we'll get
whatever versus like a Bottoms Up which
maybe I have these wrong but it's like
well I only need to get five of these
these folks to like whatever and I can
sell this many this year and whatever
and I'll build up to how many I can
reasonably sell do you find when you're
approaching a problem do you start with
six billion people and what percentage
of those are Surfers or do you start
from the bottom up for most companies I
think they start top down traditionally
mainly because the data is easier to
come by it's an easier exercise to do
right so you can hire a company to go
out and do market research for you and
get you some estimates but candy there's
so much market research out there today
that I'm surprised like most Industries
you should be able to find some data
points to get you started yeah say if
you can't find those numbers you're
probably in a market you don't
understand enough right yeah or it's too
broad right yeah you're absolutely right
but the exercise is really this at least
the way that I found it to be most
successful is you find some market
research out there and it gives you a
general sense of what the scale of the
market is and then if you have great
analytics on your platform you can learn
enough about your consumers to figure
out what segmentation actually matters
like what your Sam should be because the
market research that you find out there
is like typically just going to be very
high level and you're going to have to
cut it down
but it's up to you to determine how to
cut it down what variables do you need
to factor in are geographical variables
demographic variables is a commitment so
it's important that you kind of go from
both angles is start with market
research do some analysis of your
consumer and then try to hone in on what
a serviceable addressable Market is and
you can make it as complex or high level
as you want I mean the moment you start
factoring in competitors it starts
getting really complicated because you
have to factor and that's kind of the
next step down which is serviceable
obtainable Market is what percentage of
the market can you actually acquire
compared to the other competitors in the
market I think it's probably a little
bit detailed for this conversation but
we talk about modeling a lot and
modeling is wrong always I find that on
the line of complexity I'm always saying
the more complex you make a model the
more likely you're going to get it to
say what you want it to say and the more
likely it is to be wrong right simple is
better if you can start with the
simplest model and get answers that are
reasonable and then I don't know if you
found this but I find that it's useful
to not just revisit the same model every
time you need it but if your model's so
in complex that you can't kind of
rebuild it in a sitting then your model
might be too complex because what I also
find is nice is that if you start from
first principles and rebuild your models
once in a while one you'll rethink your
assumptions two if you get an answer
that reasonably matches your first
attempt then you have some confidence
that you know you didn't just torture
your model to say what you wanted it to
say I mean that applies not just for
adustable Market modeling that's for
building any kind of predictive thing
but yeah it's definitely something for
our listeners in appland we have
probably a lot of folks that aren't
thinking about having to pitch investor
right having to tell some massive Tam
story but it doesn't matter you're the
investor you're investing your time do
some math and make sure that you have a
tam that seems pretty big to you because
if the smaller your Tam less that Tam's
going to grow the harder time you're
going to have it's just going to be
tougher and if you're have a small
enough Tam even winning isn't that good
of an outcome right the Tam's small
enough you know what I mean so I think
it's especially for hobbyists looking to
like build something do yourself a favor
build something a lot of people can use
it'll be more fun or build something a
small Niche want to use but then
understand that it is a small Niche and
then charge appropriately to the size of
that market but I did want to dig into
service obtainable Market I know you
kind of said it's a little too complex
to dive into but I think this is an
important thing that is part of the
modeling that is often overlooked is
that okay there's 50 million Surfers or
that's probably even high that's a tam
or Sam is actually like 20 million but
then you have like willingness to pay
and price and all those other things
that factor into like how many of those
folks in the Sam are you actually going
to convert to a subscriber and that's
the obtainable so how do you think about
that willingness to pay and then I'm
going to out Jacob and some of the early
Revenue cat employees Surfers are
notoriously cheap I think the first five
employees at Rue C were like sharing a
Surfline account so you have my Surfline
account by the way just want to point
out there that I was the I was always
paying and I have one now even though I
live in Ohio I have almost always an
annual Surfline subscript going because
it'll expire and then the next trip I
take to the coast I resubscribe so I've
made up for my sins so how do you factor
in that willingness to pay and then
obviously the goal for surf line is to
continue evolving the product and to get
more and more of that service
addressable Market to be service
obtainable market so yeah how do you
think about that willingness to pay in
modeling from Tam to Sam to S yeah
whatever so maybe we decouple them a
little bit so really what we're talking
about is price sensitivity right how
price sensitive a consumer is and even
that term is maybe a tiny bit misleading
because it has three components at least
the way I like to think about it first
is purchasing power which is what we're
traditionally talking about so if you
say like Surfers are cheap really what
you mean is that maybe it's a purchasing
power situation possibly the other two
variables are commitment like how
committed are they how passionate are
they and the last is how strong is your
value proposition it's really
relationship between those three things
and you have to assess how strong that
relationship is and where the gaps are
so in surfing for example if you think
think about where most Surfers like
let's say domestically where they're
located typically in California and
coastal areas or Hawaii and coastal
areas and so those areas aren't cheap to
live in and when we've done market
research we found that actually the
audience is a bit more affluent than you
would originally believe now when you go
to Commitment like I have not met a more
committed passionate group of people
than Surfers these are people waking up
at 400 in the morning to drive 2 hours
away to catch a swell window of an hour
and go surfing then going to work after
that yeah and then going to work right
after like sitting in a 5 mil w suit in
55 degree water for a couple hours so
commitment level super high and then the
last piece is like how strong your value
proposition is that's the kind of
relationship we're talking about so if
you think about Sam and s in that kind
of light really the first thing to think
about is like how strong your value
proposition really is and then over time
how much stronger do you believe it's
going to get that's a huge benefit of
Premium models because over time is your
value proposition gets stronger you have
the ability or the time benefit of being
able to convert people that are on
platform
and so that's the first big one is like
how strong is your value prop and how
much stronger is it going to get over
time and how does that compare to the
other value propositions in the market
so for Surfline for example there are a
lot of free competitors out there
there's not many paid competitors and so
we're targeting a consumer that would be
willing to pay for this product so the
commitment level has to be pretty high
compared to somebody who surfs maybe
once a month or once every couple months
maybe the free products that are out
there on the market are a better fit for
them however over time we have plans to
produce a product that would be a better
fit for these other consumers that are
targeted by other audiences so there's
no one size fits all but you really need
to make sure that you're aligned with
those three variables and understand
really where the gaps are and what
you're trying to influence when
strategically thinking about some how
much do you just write off like a
certain percentage of Surfers no matter
what the value prop just aren't going to
be willing to pay or is it a price
sensitivity where it's less that they're
not willing to pay anything it's just
they're not willing to pay the price
that makes sense for surfine fairly
certain if all the surf line cams were
free everybody would just use it there's
not a ton of other
cams yeah again it's a hard thing to
calculate I think the way that we go
about it is we have a pretty large free
audience and we can do quite a bit of
analysis and understanding how much
purchasing power price sensitivity
affects people's conversion rates and
how that changes over time as our
product gets better there will always be
a cohort of users it's not willing to
pay and it's especially important for a
company like Surfline right because
Surfline historically used to be free
there's a lot of companies that have
gone through this transition where they
had a free product and now it's behind a
pay wall so New York Times is another
good example and that intrinsically
causes challenges because you've
educated a consumer that something used
to be free and now it's something that
they have to pay for which again also is
something that influences whether
somebody's willing to pay for something
or not because again they just believe
it should be free so at least in my mind
there's no rule of thumb but there will
always be cohorts of users doesn't
matter what industry it is and doesn't
matter how much purchasing power they
have that will not be willing to pay for
the product and so you just do your best
to quantify how large that cohort is
either through surveying or through un
product analysis and then you factor
that into your models which will
intrinsically be wrong and then we'll
make a decision to go from there this
did get really nerdy but these are the
things as a consumer subscription
business you need to be thinking about
and I think you're right you kicked it
off saying you see a lot of mistakes
like I see that too A lot of people like
oh yeah there's 50 million golfers in
the US we only need 5% penetration or
whatever to build a great business and
then we're going to get to 50% 2018
being like Oh there's a hundred billion
dollar in subscription Revenue I just
need to get 1% of that and then you
learn well 85% of that is locked up in
four apps and they are never touching
their infrastructure ever again so like
okay now my numbers changed a little bit
maybe the benefit of naiv in those early
days if you totally understood your
challenges you might not ever start
nobody ever got hurt from knowing more
right yeah by going through the modeling
exercise as we've discussed and I think
you've had some really great thoughts
that I hope our audience can take away
from this to do their own modeling to
just understand where their business is
going and understand where to invest and
how much to charge and taking those
three variables you shared it's like if
you understand that your service
addressable Market is much smaller then
like you said you do need to focus more
on arpo and like build something that's
super valuable to that smaller service
addressable Market versus trying to to
be the $20 a year everybody's going to
subscribe Well everybody's not going to
subscribe if even if it is $20 a year
and if your Market small you don't want
to be $20 a year you want to be $120 a
year so I think this all super important
for anybody in this industry to be
thinking about and then that leads into
the next topic I wanted to cover is
premium strategy so you understand okay
certain percentage aren't going to pay
they're part of our service addressable
Market they're going to get some value
from our product even if they're not
willing to pay so how do you approach
that at Surfline of offering some amount
of value for free to those users who
don't want to pay or do have a level of
price sensitivity that you're not
delivering quite enough value to get
them over that hump when you think about
freemium really what the hypothesis is
is that you can launch this fremium
model that over time will reduce your
CAC that's the goal is hey I'm building
this model that will result in lower
customer acquisition costs than if I
don't have it and there's a lot of
things to factor in when determining
whether that's true or not right because
both models a premium model or a
completely paid model can be successful
and there's thousands of examples for
Surfline it's kind of funny again
because we didn't originally get into
the business and say hey we're going to
have this premium model right we were
free and then we transitioned to paid
over a long period of time but because
we started as a free product over the
years we amassed a very large audience
on the platform that was habituated to
the products that we were offering and
it was really important for an industry
like surf because if you're a new Surfer
getting into the sport you don't really
know why surf forecasting matters right
like you're going to go when you go you
don't understand like why when I learned
everything I know about predicting surf
from the human written surf forecast for
the Bay Area from surf line you talk
about habitual first thing in the
morning surfing or not pulled my phone
before I look at Twitter i' open
Surfline yeah yeah it was a great
strategy because over time what we did
was we habituated users and we educated
them on the products that we offered and
so we ended up creating this great
funnel that allowed us to educate users
on the free product and then over time
as they found value in what we were
offering they would want the full Suite
of product features and then subscribe
and so We've Ended a place today where
we don't spend any money on paid
acquisition and we have this great
growth funnel that effectively we're
organically getting people into the
freezer experience we educate them
habituate them and then there's some
cohort of Surfers that get very
committed and love the product and end
up subscribing and so we built this
great growth engine I will say a few
things one is like this does not happen
overnight so if you're contemplating
starting a free or premium model
business there's going to be pain in the
beginning for sure for a few reasons the
first one being that you're adding an
extra step right if people just hit a
pay wall there's some percentage that
are just going to convert and move
through but you're adding an extra step
a free experience it's going to take
time for people to understand what
you're offering you're going to get it
wrong a bunch of times in the beginning
you have to draw a bunch of borders too
I always found difficult like every part
of your product has to have a line in it
somewhere and it gets really complicated
to
it absolutely does and again you're
going to have to test and iterate and
test and iterate and there's a kind of
like magic rule here with freemium
models that I tell everyone that's try
and follow you're really trying to
balance increasing conversion versus
increasing free user retention it's very
important that you do that if you don't
do that your premium model will most
likely not be a success and here's why I
say that right so you launch a premium
model and over time you see that hey
we've optimized our premium model and
now conversions doubled fantastic but
it's coming at the cost of free user
retention and we're not retaining free
users nearly as effectively as we were
before and so what will happen is every
month if the retention is poor enough
the size of your free audience starts to
decline and the pool of free users that
you can convert to a paid product it's
smaller so it doesn't matter if you
double the conversion rate on half the
audience you haven't gone anywhere
exactly and that's the biggest issue
that I see with premium models out in
the industry is there hasn't been enough
testing and they've weighted too high on
one versus the other now if you have to
wait more on one than the other it's
probably better to wait on free user
retention if you have the capital to
kind of sustain less conversion for a
period of time because as a product
owner or whoever you have to believe
that your product is going to improve
over time and the great thing about a
free experience is it buys you a bit of
time to optimize your product and make
it better because the ultimate rule here
is like hey we're just trying to build
great products that people want to pay
for and you'd much rather have people on
your product rather than off market
right if they come in and they hit a pay
W and they don't want to subscribe it's
much harder to go out into the market
and find them with social media and then
convince them to come back versus on
platform your messaging very clear your
value propositions are easy to
communicate and so there's a huge
benefit in being able to communicate
people as the product gets better I.E
like dualingo has absolutely smashed in
this category over years they've
optimized and optimized optimized it
still doesn't seem like a paid product
even though it makes a ton of money
right such a magical hack but they how
long they were like six or seven years
in Market before they started to
monetize in way is crazy yeah and I
can't tell you how much they've
optimized that free experience they've
made it so fun and they habituate their
users right so like learning isn't
intrinsically something that all
consumers comeing in like this is fun
right but dingo's found the way to
optimize their experience in a way that
you come in you use the free product
over time you start having fun using the
product and they've realized like that's
the best way to convert somebody to
paying subscription but it takes years
and years in optimizations and there's
so many different premium models by the
way it's not not just one model out
there dingo is a great example of that
right they've had gems and a premium
subscription and like lots of different
things that they've tried I don't know
I'm sure they've experimented with ads
at some point too I don't know if it's
in the full product but we had a guest
from dingo on a few months ago and the
experimentation there is crazy which is
what you probably need right to like
swim through that fremium universe and
find an optimal the behavior you
mentioned of trading off between free
user retention and conversion and then
focusing on the product makes me think
of sort of submodel always I think about
is like value creation right your app is
going to create value conversion rates
and pay walls and all this stuff is a
motion of capturing value and if you
capture all of the value users aren't
going to hang around there needs to be a
value Surplus that they're able to
maintain and I think that's what you're
kind of describing there is if you
squeeze those free user so that there's
no value there's not enough value there
for them because you've shut it off or
like close it you're actually going to
end up in a worse position versus
spending your time actually just
increasing the big pie that you're
trying to capture value from then your
job gets a little bit easier right I'm a
fan of monetizing early because I do
think it gives real numbers and real
measurements on things but that can go
too far and not get enough people in
also in the early early days when you
have just like small numbers if your app
is so paywalled that you can't get
enough people in to really learn you're
going to have a hard time going anywhere
because like you can't improve a product
without users like I think a lot of
folks like to pretend that they're smart
and like Steve Jobs or whatever and they
can just tell you what's a great product
but I don't think even Steve did that
really right like everybody's doing it
in conversation with users it's hard
with premium because so many of the
benefits of Premium are non pnl line
items it's like growth Word of Mouth
things like this you mentioned
acquisition and that you you don't do
paid acquisition or like it's all
organic like what's your primary channel
is it SEO like people searching surf
spots you know for apps it's really
tough but I imagine you guys have a big
web presence too we do and remember
we've been around for decades so the
brand presence is kind of ubiquitous in
the industry so there's a lot of word
MTH but SEO is a pretty big one we're
getting a lot of traffic through the App
Store as well I would say SEO if people
aren't finding out through their buddies
that are going in surfing that I think
that's how I came in was that way but
you also do a lot of content too right
you do some Sur vids and written content
if I'm not mistaken we do right so
everything on the platform is really
content so when we write a surf report
for a certain location if Surfers are
going to a new area and trying to figure
out where to surf they'll Google what
are the surf conditions at elto or
wherever and they'll land on surf line
or a competitor's page so there's a lot
of traffic coming into those spot pages
and individual surf reports but we do a
lot of content as well we have a big
editorial alarm that writes not just
about surf conditions and kind what's
happening there but we write a lot about
news and other topics as well yeah it's
interesting what we tend to call free or
organic when it's like we actually like
Revenue cat doesn't do a lot of paid
acquisition either but we do a lot of
work to get
acquisition
right how does the conversion over time
play out for surf line specifically cuz
I've talked to a lot of of app
businesses where oh yeah if somebody
doesn't convert in that first session
they just never convert but I've always
kind of thought that that means premium
probably is not working that's not a
good fremium strategy if that is the
case and it needs a rethink so I would
imagine that you do see some positive
year-over-year growth in being able to
convert those free users into paid
subscribers yeah so I think probably
what that person's referring to and I
see this with most products is when
people download the app even if you have
a fremium model typically the largest
percentage of your conversion will
happen pretty quickly like people will
convert within the first seven days and
then there's a trickle of conversion
over time now again with freemium like
the hypothesis here is that the value
that you put behind the pay wall will
continue to grow and the value of that
product will continue to improve and so
it's up to you to articulate that value
and make sure there's balance between
the value that's in front of the pay
wall and behind the pay wall so a lot of
companies that's where they fail is
there's just a misbalance between the
value in front and behind the pay wall
and you need to do a lot of testing the
last three years we've tested and tested
and tested different options right not
just messaging or what's payall and
what's not but the different models as
an example there's a pretty typical
model where a consumer gets unlimited
access to a limited amount of features
right they come in and like these three
features are free but you can use them
as often as you want there's another
model that's pretty typical the New York
Times model where you come in and you
get limited access to not an unlimited
amount of features but to some features
so you come in and after your third time
of using these features you're no longer
allowed to use them and you see this in
gaming and all kinds of different
Industries and there's pros and cons to
both and we've tested both you know
ultimately I'm a bigger fan of not
limiting engagement because if you can
create some kind of habituation with a
free product is fantastic they'll come
in on their own and if someone's coming
in 10 15 times a month that gives you
more opportunity to message them educate
them about the product that you are
offering so there's some imbalance
likely for a lot of these other
companies and you have to determine
whether it's a value problem or if it's
a model problem and there's no way to
really figure it out until you test it
you talked about it being that trickle
over time I guess my question was over
time for surf line as that value prop
has increased as you figured things out
as youve done testing does that trickle
start to become a little bit of a stream
and grow into a more meaningful thing
like is that trickle growing like is the
premium model actually working in that
way over time where that trickle does
become a meaningful part of the business
of more and more people subscribing in
year one after a habituation versus that
like oh still 98% of our Revenue comes
from people who signed up like day one
I'll anecdotally add some here and I
might not be technically a premium user
but I've oscillate between a premium
user and a paid user depending on the
season of my life so if I'm spending a
lot of time on the coast or whatever if
I'm there for even a couple weeks like I
will buy a subscription and then I will
let it expire when I'm not at the coast
anymore I become a free user I still can
get cams I have to watch an ad for
there's an ad for board shorts that used
to play at the beginning of like every
Surfline video from 5 years ago that I
will never forget but you just watch it
CU you're like well I got to see the cam
and you do that until one day you're fed
up and you transition over but I might
be an interesting case because you talk
about that propensity to pay like I can
afford a Surline subscription right
there's probably some users who never do
or it's never going to be a thing they
do and not to steal your answer Paul but
like David I don't even know if that's
necessary totally right like the value
of a premium user base has value and
ideally you want set up to have value in
itself you convert them great but they
also provide Word of Mouth they also
provide feedback in surfline's case you
guys also monetize with advertising so
they provide a base you can monetize for
them as well so yeah before on the spot
like are you actually making money out
these people I'm like yeah like in lots
of ways we definitely are I'm hoping you
bought that pair of board shorts on that
ad still can see it he's like oh this
perfect right-hander he's like in the
barrel and then I do remember the brand
it was probably vcom and you guys should
keep advertising on fly so here I'm
doing you a favor love it over the past
five years we have seen a pretty big
increase in conversion of that free
audience typically the way it works is
like if you launch a new product or we
add new cams to a certain area you'll
see an uplift pretty quickly and then
it'll slow down over time but your
Baseline conversion over time continues
to improve I haven't seen too many
instances not here or even in other
products where you launch something and
your conversion just kind of doubles
overnight or anything like that but what
you'll see is that you'll launch a new
product you'll get a bunch of early
adopters that come in subscribe but your
Baseline conversion after those early
adopters have been kind of normalized is
a bit higher than what it was before so
that's kind of the model is over time
you're hoping that every year your
premium conversion is a little bit
better and a little bit better and a
little bit better but the size of your
free audience has not gone down and if
you can do that then you kind of have a
recipe for Success yeah how does AD
sales and sponsorships work in that
Jacob kind of mentioned that you are
monetizing that free base and with
unskippable video ads the cams are good
you got to watch the ads it's the deal
how does that side of the monetization
play out we have an ad sales team and
traditionally we went to Market and we
would sell media packages and that was
kind of our strategy and we'd monetize
the free audience but over time we've
slowly started to transition our focus a
little bit so today while we still sell
traditional media packages our Focus has
shifted a little bit to finding ways to
connect the consumer in The Advertiser
for a premium audience in a native way
and so the best way for us to do that is
to find ways for Brands to give value
directly to the consumer so imagine your
consumer behind the pay wall Brand's
trying to reach them it's not really
easy to put ads behind a payall it's not
a great user experience I don't
recommend it so instead what we've been
trying to do is find partnership deals
with these Brands where the brand will
give the consumer some kind of exclusive
discount or Early Access or something
that the consumer didn't have before
doesn't have access to and then we'll
Market that perk or promotion natively
to our consumers behind the pay wall and
so again we kind of are doing both we're
doing a traditional media strategy but
we're also pivoting in a big way to
trying to get as much value to the
subscribers as possible right that's our
number one goal you're thinking about
those as two separate strategies right
so you're doing more traditional display
ads or whatever you guys are using for
the non-subscribed audience and then for
the described audience also thinking
about ways you can Tastefully I'm sure
monetize behind the pay wall yeah it's
the same strategy right we're going to
Brands and trying to figure out if there
is an offering that makes sense for them
behind the pay wall versus in front of
the pay wall but usually what we put
behind the pay walls is very well
received right a consumer will come in
and they'll like as an example maybe
they get a discount to a new surf Park
that opens in their area and it's a
Surfline only discount and so we're not
going in there and like bombarding them
with ads or anything like that we come
in and say hey there's new perk you guys
get early access to the surf park or you
guys get a discount courtesy of whoever
and the brand wins because we're
monetizing in a native way which is
traditionally it performs way better
than if we just put a banner ad
somewhere and the consumer wins because
they're getting some kind of incremental
value that they didn't have before
imagine that's a really good audience to
sell because you've kind of proven they
have some sort of disposable income in
terms of cpis I guess versus your free
audience it's going to be pretty good
right well one I haven't noticed I've
been a premium subscriber on and off and
I was like I never felt advertised too
so Kudos but we don't talk about that
all that much David on this podcast
about ways of monetizing a premium
audience you know you talk about that
RPO strategy right increasing your RPO
at some point your subscription probably
reaches the value Peak and you're not
going to be able to go much further you
just can start to think creatively about
what are other ways that we can engage
with our audience bring them value again
create value and capture it right which
can be bringing them eating offers and
things like this and it's probably a
little bit of a narrow path to walk but
I think it can be done I think the
monetizing of the free users and
understanding the value we've talked
about that a bit on the past few
episodes about understanding the value
that those free users are bringing and
like we were talking about here driving
user acquisition without having to do a
ton of paid user acquisition that kind
of thing it's like when you understand
that it helps inform the strategy for
freemium but then the other layer that I
think you all have figured out that a
lot of others haven't is effectively
monetizing those free users as well
getting some value back out through
these sponsorships through the
unskippable video ads and things like
that so I think du lingo is a great
example they don't monetize that free
base at all I will be curious like they
just crossed a 10 billion doll valuation
they hit a ceiling on their paid side
and start to think about that I mean
yeah we may see some brand Partnerships
and ads and other things make their way
into dualingo over time as they have to
monetize that free user base more
strongly to keep the growth going as
they've saturated the kind of
willingness to pay and whatnot but
anyway so much more I'd love to talk to
you about but we are needing to wrap up
so anything else you wanted to share as
we're wrapping up is surf line hiring
anything exciting coming down the pipe
that you wanted to share especially with
our subscription app nerd folks who
listen to this podcast C I don't know if
there's anything too interesting we are
going to be releasing a whole Suite of
new product features this year so anyone
who uses product Lookout we're going to
have a bunch of cool new features some
really cool stuff around camera
intelligence that we haven't released
before so I think that'll be Innovative
and really improve the Surfers
experience so that's what I'm most
excited about otherwise really stoked I
appreciate you guys having me on the
podcast was a lot of fun hi thanks
Paul thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub
[Music]